<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: COPYING.xml,v 1.1 2018/12/20 16:54:31 jjg Exp $ -->
<copying>
  <authors>
    <author href="https://www.pnnl.gov/science/staff/staff_info.asp?staff_num=9023">
      <name>Jamie R. Nuñez</name>
      <org>Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</org>
    </author>
    <author href="https://www.pnnl.gov/science/staff/staff_info.asp?staff_num=8348">
      <name>Christopher R. Anderton</name>
      <org>Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</org>
    </author>
    <author href="https://www.pnnl.gov/science/staff/staff_info.asp?staff_num=8507">
      <name>Ryan S. Renslow</name>
      <org>Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</org>
    </author>
  </authors>
  <license>
    <informal>BSD-like</informal>
    <year>2018</year>
    <text>
Copyright (c) 2017, Battelle Memorial Institute

1.  Battelle Memorial Institute (hereinafter Battelle) hereby grants
permission to any person or entity lawfully obtaining a copy of this software
and associated documentation files (hereinafter “the Software”) to
redistribute and use the Software in source and binary forms, with or without
modification. Such person or entity may use, copy, modify, merge, publish,
distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and may permit
others to do so, subject to the following conditions:

+ Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
list of conditions and the following disclaimers.

+ Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

+ Other than as used herein, neither the name Battelle Memorial Institute or
Battelle may be used in any form whatsoever without the express written
consent of Battelle.

2.  THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
"AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL BATTELLE OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
(INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES;
LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON
ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    </text>
  </license>
  <src>
    <format>text</format>
    <link
        href="https://github.com/pnnl/cmaputil/blob/master/colormaps/cividis.txt"
        >colour stops</link>
    <remark>RGB values from the cmaputil GitHub repository</remark>
  </src>
  <distribute>
    <qgis distribute="yes" license="otherok"/>
  </distribute>
</copying>
