<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" 
"../../resources/schema/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
	<header>
		<title>QGIS User Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Version 0.1pre1 (Moroz)</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="Gary Sherman" email="sherman at mrcc.com"/>
			<person name="Tim Sutton" email="tim at linfiniti.com"/>
		</authors>
		<notice>This document is under development</notice>
	</header>
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Introduction</title>
		
			<p>Quantum GIS (QGIS) is designed to be a Geographic Information System (GIS) 
built for Linux/Unix. QGIS currently offers basic support for vector, raster, and database formats.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Current Features</title>
			<ul>
				<li>Support for spatially enabled PostgreSQL tables using PostGIS</li>
				<li>Support for ESRI shapefiles and other vector formats support by the OGR library</li>
				<li>Identify features</li>
				<li>Display attribute table</li>
				<li>Select features</li>
				<li>Persistent selections</li>
				<li>Save projects</li>
				<li>Support for raster formats supported by the GDAL library</li>
				<li>Change vector symbology (single, graduated, and continuous)</li>
				<li>Display raster data such as digital elevation models, aerial photography or
				landsat imagery</li>
				<li>Change raster symbology (grayscale, pseudocolor and multiband RGB)</li>
				<li>Export to Mapserver map file</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Getting Started</title>
			<p>This section gives you a quick overview of running QGIS and examining data 
			available on the QGIS web page.
			</p>
			<section>
				<title>Installation</title>
				<p>Installation of QGIS is documented in the <link href="site:install">Installation Guide</link>.
				</p>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Sample Data</title>
				<p>If you do not have any GIS data, you can obtain a dataset for Alaska (which will be used as the
				basis for the examples and screenshots provided in this document) from the 
				<link href="http://qgis.sourceforge.net/qgis_sample_data.tar.gz">the QGIS web site</link></p>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Starting QGIS</title>
				<p>
				Assuming the QGIS is installed in the PATH, you can start QGIS by typing:
				<code>qgis</code>.</p>
				<p>
				In addition, you can start QGIS by specifying one or more datafiles on the commandline. For example, 
				assuming you are in your data directory, you could start QGIS with two shapefiles and a raster file set to 
				load on startup:
				</p>
				<p><code>qgis ak_shade.tif alaska.shp majrivers.shp </code></p>		
				<p><img alt="QGIS Load Data On Start" src="images/qgis_load_data_on_startup.png"/></p>
				<note>Your window decorations (title bar, etc.) may appear different depending on your operating system
				and window manager</note>				
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>The QGIS main window</title>
				<p>
				When QGIS starts, an empty window is displayed as shown below.
				<img alt="QGIS Main Window" src="images/qgis_mainwindow01.png"/>
				</p>
				<p>The QGIS main window is divided into five areas:</p>
				<ol>
					<li>The menu bar</li>
					<li>The tool bar</li>
					<li>The map legend</li>
					<li>The map view</li>
					<li>The status bar</li>
				</ol>
				<p>These five parts of the main QGIS are described in more detail in the following sections</p>
				<section>
					<title>The QGIS menu bar</title>
					<p>The menu bar provides access to various QGIS features using a standard windows 
					heirachical menu.</p>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>The QGIS toolbars</title>
					<p>QGIS has toolbars that provide quick access to commonly used functions. These are:</p>
					<ul>
						<li><img alt="New Project" src="images/filenew.png"/> - Start a new QGIS project. If you 
						already have a project ope, you will be asked if you would like to save the existing one first.</li>
						<li><img alt="Open Project" src="images/open.png"/> - Open a previously saved project.</li>
						<li><img alt="Save Project" src="images/filesave.png"/> - Save the current project.</li>
						<li><img alt="Save Project As" src="images/filesaveas.png"/> - Save project under a new file name.</li>
						<li><img alt="Add Postgis Layer(s)" src="images/gis_add_pg_layer.png"/> - Add one or more layers 
						stored in a PostgreSQL/Postgis geodatabase to the map view.</li>
						<li><img alt="Add Vector Layer(s)" src="images/gis_add_vector_layer.png"/> - Add one or more layers 
						stored on disk as shapefiles to the map view.</li>
						<li><img alt="Add Raster Layers" src="images/gis_add_raster_layer.png"/> - Add one or more raster layers
						to the map view. </li>
						<li><img alt="Reload" src="images/reload20x20.png"/> - Reload the current map view (refreshes display)</li>
						<li><img alt="Zoom In" src="images/zoomin.png"/> - Zoom in the map display by dragging a rectangle</li>
						<li><img alt="Zoom Out" src="images/viewmag-.png"/> - Zoom out of the map display by dragging a rectangle.
						Dragging a small rectangle will zoom out a long way, dragging a large rectangle will zoom out a little way.</li>
						<li><img alt="Zoom Full Extent" src="images/gis_view_all.png"/> - Zoom out until all features in all map layers
						are visible.</li>
						<li><img alt="Zoom to Selected" src="images/gis_zoom_to_selected.png"/> - Zoom to fit all selected features in the 
						map view.</li>
						<li><img alt="Pan" src="images/gis_pan.png"/> - Pan in the map display area.</li>
						<li><img alt="Zoom to Previous" src="images/back20x20.png"/> - Zoom to last extents.</li>
						<li><img alt="Identify" src="images/gis_identify.png"/> - Show information about a feature (applies only to vector data).</li>
						<li><img alt="Select Features" src="images/select_features.png"/> - Select features in the map display (applies only to vector data).</li>
						<li><img alt="Show Attributes" src="images/table.png"/> - Show the attribute table for the selected layer (applies only to vector data).</li>										
					</ul>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>The QGIS map legend</title>
					<p>The map legend area is used to set the visibility and z-ordering of layers.
					Z-ordering means that layers listed nearer the top of the legend are drawn over
					layers listed lower down in the legend. The checkbox in each legend entry can be useed 
					to show/hire that layer.</p>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>The QGIS map view</title>
					<p>This is the 'business end' of QGIS - maps are displayed in this area! The map 
					displayed in this window will depend on the vector and raster layers you have chosen 
					to load (see sections that follow for more info on this). The map view can be panned (shifting
					to focus of the map display to another region), zoomed in and out, and supports various other 
					actions as described in the toolbar description above.</p>
					<p>The map view and the legend  are tightly bound to each other - the maps in view 
					reflect changes you make in the legend area.</p>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>The QGIS map status bar</title>
					<p>The status bar shows you your current position in map coordinate (e.g. meters or decimal 
					degress) as the mouse pointer is moved accross the map view. </p>
				</section>				
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Working with vector data</title>
			<section>
				<title>Loading vector data</title>
				<p>To load one or more shapefiles, click on the Add Layer button 
				<img alt="Add Layer" src="images/gis_add_vector_layer.png"/>. </p>
				<p>The <em>Select one or more layers to add</em> dialog box will be displayed.
				<img alt="Select layers" src="images/add_layer_dialog.png"/></p>
				<p>Navigate to the directory where the shapefiles reside. Select one or
				more files and click ok to load them.</p>
				<p>When QGIS loads a layer, it assigns a random color to it as shown 
				below.</p>
				<p><img alt="Shapefiles loaded into QGIS" src="images/loaded_shapefiles.png"/>
				</p>
				<p>
				Obviously QGIS's choice of colors is not very pleasing in this case.
				</p>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Changing Symbology</title>
				<p>
				To make the layer more appealing, open the Layer Properties 
				dialog by right-clicking on a layer name
				in the table of contents (left side of the QGIS window) and
				selecting <em>Properties</em>.
				</p>
				<p>
				<img alt="Layer Properties" src="images/layer_properties.gif"/>
				</p>
				<p>
				If you like, change the display name of the layer by editing
				the <em>Display name</em> field. Click on the <em>Symbology</em>
				tab and click on the <em>Outline color</em> and <em>Fill color</em>
				and select a new color from the color chooser. You can also change the
				line width if desired.</p>
				<p>
				<img alt="Changing colors" src="images/change_symbology.gif"/>
				</p>
				<p>After making the changes, click Ok to apply the changes to
				the layer. Note that the alaska layer has been renamed to Alaska and the
				color has been changed to a light green:</p>
				<p>
				<img alt="Changing colors" src="images/changed_symbology.gif"/>
				</p>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Identifying a Feature</title>
				<p>QGIS provides a useful tool (<img alt="Identify" src="images/gis_identify.png"/> - the 'identify' tool) that allows you to click on a vector feature (
				point, line or polygon) and view information about that feautre. The information displayed is 
				retrieved from the Postgres database (in the case of Postgis layers) or from the .dbf file
				associated with the shapefile you are insecting.</p>

			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
		  	<title>Working with raster data</title>
		  	<section>
		  		<title>What is raster data?</title>
		  		<p>Raster data in GIS are matrices of discrete cells that represent features on, above or below the earth's surface. Each 
		  		cell in the raster grid is the same size, and cells are usually rectangular (in QGIS they will always be rectangular. 
		  		Typical raster datasets include 'remote sensing' data (such as aerial photography and satellite imagery) and modelled data
		  		(such as an elevation matrix).</p>
		  		<p>Raster data typically do not have an associated database record for each cell (unlike in vector data where it is normal
		   		for each feature to have an associated database record).</p>
				<p>In GIS, a raster layer would have geopositioning data associated with it which will allow it to be positioned
				correctly in the map display to allow other vector and raster data to be overlayed with it. QGIS, can read this 
				geopositioning data to facilitate properly displaying map overlays.</p>
		  	</section>
		  	<section>
		  		<title>Raster formats supported in QGIS.</title>
		  		<p>QGIS supports a number of different raster formats. Currently tested formats include:</p>
		  		<ul>
		  		<li>Arc/Info Binary Grid</li>
		  		<li>Arc/Info ASCII Grid</li>
		  		<li>Grass Raster</li>
		  		<li>GeoTIFF</li>
		  		<li>Spatial Data Transfer Standard Grids (with some limitations)</li>
		  		<li>USGS ASCII DEM</li>
		  		<li>Erdas Imagine</li>
		  		</ul>
		  		<p>Because the raster implmentation in QGIS is based on the GDAL abstraction library, orther raster formats implemented
		  		in GDAL are also likely to work, but have not yet been tested. See 
		  		<link href="http://remotesensing.org/gdal/formats_list.html">the GDAL Raster Formats page</link> for more details.</p>
		  	</section>
		  	<section>
		  		<title>Loading raster data in QGIS</title>
		  		<p>Raster layers are loaded either by clicking on the <img alt="Load Raster" src="images/gis_add_raster_layer.png"/> icon
				or by selecting the View->Add Raster Layer menu option. More than one layer can be loaded at the same time
				by holding down the Control key and clicking on multiple items in the file dialog.</p>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Symbolisation and properties for raster layers</title>
				<p>Symbolisation of raster layers is achieved by right clicking on a raster layer legend entry and choosing 'properties':
				on the popup menu that appears:</p>
				<p>
				<img alt="Raster Properties Popup" src="images/qgis_raster_popup_properties_selected.png"/>
				</p>
				<p>On the properties dialog for rasters you will see there are three tabs:</p>
				<section>
					<title>The general properties tab</title>
					<p>
					<img alt="Raster Properties Popup" src="images/qgis_raster_properties_general_tab.png"/>
					</p>	
					<p>The legend tab displays basic information aboug the selected raster - including its
					dimensions (in pixels) and its display name in the legend.</p>
				</section>			
				<section>
					<title>The symbology properties tab</title>
					<p>
					<img alt="Raster Properties Popup" src="images/qgis_raster_properties_symbology_tab.png"/>
					</p>	
					
					
					<p>QGIS supports three forms of raster layer:</p>
					<ul>
						<li>Single Band Grayscale Rasters</li>
						<li>Palette Based RGB Rasters</li>
						<li>Multiband RGB Rasters</li>
					</ul>
					<p>From these three basic layer types, eight forms of symbolised raster display can be used:</p>
					<ol>
						<li>Single Band Grayscale</li>
						<li>Single Band Pseudocolor</li>
						<li>Paletted Grayscale (where only the red, green or blue component of the image is displayed)</li>
						<li>Paletted Pseudocolor (where only the red, green or blue component of the image is displayed, but using a pseudocolor algorithm)</li>
						<li>Paletted RGB</li>
						<li>Multiband Grayscale (using only one of the bands to display the image)</li>
						<li>Mulitiband Pseudocolor (using only one of the bands shown in pseudocolor)</li>
						<li>Multiband RGB (using any combination of three bands)</li>
					</ol>
					<p>QGIS has the capability to invert the colours in a given layer so that light 
					colors become dark (and dark colors become light). Use the 'Invert Color Map' checkbox 
					to enable / disable this behaviour.</p>
				
					<p>QGIS has the capability to display each raster layer at varying transparency levels. Use
					the transparency slider to indicate to what extent the underlying layers (if any) should
					be visible though the current raster layer.</p>
				
					<p>QGIS has the capability to restrict the data displayed to show only cells whose values are
					within a given number of standard diviations of the mean for the layer. This is useful
					when you have one or two cells with abnormally high values in a raster grid that are having a
					negative impact on the rendering of the raster. This option is only available for pseudocolor
					images.</p>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>The raster statistics properties tab</title>
					<p>
					<img alt="Raster Properties Popup" src="images/qgis_raster_properties_statistics_tab.png"/>
					</p>
					<p>This tab displays statistics about each band in the current raster layer. Statistics are
					gathered on a 'need to know' basis, so it may well be that a given layer's statistics have 
					not yet been collected.</p>	
					<p>Statistics for a layer are gathered when pseudocolor rendering is selected and the 'apply'
					button is pressed.</p>
					<note>Gathering statistics for a layer can be time consuming. Please be patient while 
					QGIS examines your data!</note>
				</section>
			</section>
				
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Creating a QGIS mime type</title>
			<p>If you are a KDE user, you can create a mime type that associates GIS files with QGIS. This is useful
			because it allows you to click on a shapefile (for example) in konqueror and the file will be loaded in a 
			new instance of QGIS.
			</p>
			<p>
			<link href="http://sourceforge.net/"><img src="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=55820&amp;type=1" width="88" height="31" alt="SourceForge.net Logo"/></link>
			</p>
		</section>		
		<section>
			<title>Acknowledgments</title>
			<p>Hosting for the QGIS project is generously provided by Sourceforge.
			</p>
			<p>
			<link href="http://sourceforge.net/"><img src="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=55820&amp;type=1" width="88" height="31" alt="SourceForge.net Logo"/></link>
			</p>
			<p>Please see the Help->About->Contributors for a list of people who have donated their time to the QGIS project.</p>
		</section>		
	</body>
	<footer>
		<legal>© 2003 Gary Sherman</legal>
	</footer>
</document>
